Guide to the Gail and Stephen Rudin collection of Civil War letters, 1861-1865.
Rudin, Gail and Stephen collection of Civil War letters
- Series II. Letters from Dr. William Harrison Githens
  - Writer: William Harrison Githens Writer's location: Various Addressee: Wife, 2/1862-1862 (Box 4, Folder 31)
    Four letters, two are just dealer description, not the actual letter, all are copies. Discuss Fort Payne, Kentucky, Bird's Point Missouri, drunkenness, buying a horse, Pittsburgh Landing, Tennessee River, Cairo, illness of men.
    Number of pages: 8 pages of photocopies
  - Writer: William Harrison Githens Writer's location: Philadelphia, PA Addressee: Wife, 4/1862-12/1862 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    Six letters, all are copies. Discuss taking musket balls from trees as keepsakes, Continental Hotel in Philadelphia Pennsylvania, Cousin Sammy Scull, taking classes in Philadelphia and wondering about being able to afford a graduating, visiting the mint to see money being made and the Academy of Sciences, also other sites of Philadelphia including the Liberty Bell and Independence Hall. Mentions church attendees in their furs, wishing he and his wife were rich to travel, wanting to be home for Christmas.
    Number of pages: 16 pages of photocopies
  - Writer: William Harrison Githens Writer's location: Various Addressee: Wife and daughter Louise, 1863-7/1863 (Box 4, Folder 33)
    Nine letters, several are just dealer description not the actual letter, all are copies. Discuss troop movements, homesickness, battle at Franklin Tennessee, botched hanging of Confederate spies, taking over a confederate camp, with map, encouragement to daughter to keep up studies,
    Number of pages: 17 pages of photocopies
  - Writer: William Harrison Githens Writer's location: Various Addressee: Wife, 10/1863-12/1863 (Box 4, Folder 34)
    Six letters, all are copies. Discuss wounded soldiers, hunger, measles, mumps, smallpox, blistered feet, Confederate deserters, Chattanooga Tennessee, Chickamauga Station battle, sketches of soldier life.
    Number of pages:21 pages of photocopies
  - Writer: William Harrison Githens Writer's location: Various Addressee: Wife, 1/1864-1864 (Box 4, Folder 35)
    Seven letters, several are just dealer description not the actual letter, all are copies. Discuss a brother digging grave for another brother, re-electing Lincoln, citizen rations, Georgia, bringing decaying remains in from the battlefield, church.
  - Writer: William Harrison Githens Writer's location: Various Addressee: Wife, 2/1864-4/1864 (Box 4, Folder 36)
    Five letters, several are just dealer description not the actual letter, all are copies. Discuss Chattanooga, starving rebels, buying a house, bad vaccines causing the soldiers sores, retrieving dead from the field.
    Number of pages:18 pages of photocopies
  - Writer: William Harrison Githens Writer's location: Various Addressee: Wife and daughter, 5/1864-7/1864 (Box 4, Folder 37)
    Nine letters, several are just dealer description not the actual letter, all are copies. Discuss capturing several thousand pounds of tobacco and prisoners, amputations, women, battle of Kennisaw Mountain, schoolwork of his daughter, Atlanta,
  - Writer: William Harrison Githens Writer's location: Various Addressee: Wife, 8/1864-9/1864 (Box 4, Folder 38)
    Five letters, all are copies. Discuss taking in rebel wounded and dead, severe wounds, maggots in wounds, shot to the head of Colonel, Van Vleck, rebels destroying millions of dollars of property as they retreated, people of the South relating to Yankees,
    Number of pages: 23 pages of photocopies
  - Writer: William Harrison Githens Writer's location: Various Addressee: Wife, 10/1864-12/1864 (Box 4, Folder 39)
    Six letters, all are copies. Discuss cold weather sleeping, soldier life, lack of pay, occupying a wealthy plantation mansion, U.S. Christian Commission, Christmas.
    Number of pages: 12 pages of photocopies
  - Writer: William Harrison Githens Writer's location: Various Addressee: Wife, 1/1865-5/1865 (Box 4, Folder 40)
    Nine letters, all are copies. Discuss camp life, battles, capture of Richmond and Petersburg, end of the war,
- Series III. Documents
  - Draft avoidance, December 28, 1863 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    Commutation Money receipt for avoiding the Union draft by paying a $300 fee. Yonkers, NY.
    Rudin # M-60
  - Draft avoidance: certificate of substitution, August 20, 1864; Doc S (Box 5, Folder 2)
    Form used when one person paid another to take their place in the Military Service during the Civil War. Newton Green pays Asathus A. Hart $400 to act as his substitute.
    Rudin # M-61
  - Draft avoidance, October 1, 1863; Doc S (Box 5, Folder 3)
    Certificate certifies that H.C. Gregerson is entitled to be paid $300 as a substitute for a drafted NY Policeman. Additional document acknowledges receipt of the $300.
    Rudin # M-62
  - Substitute soldier bounty payment, December 11, 1863; Doc S (Box 5, Folder 4)
    Certificate names a substitute soldier with a bounty payment of $300. Additional document releases NY Substitute Committee of claim.
    Rudin # M-63
  - Substitute broker card, Doc (Box 5, Folder 5)
    Business card for Haynes, Webb and Co. General Substitute Brokers - Bounties paid to Substitutes and Volunteers to fight in Civil War.
    Rudin # M-63A
  - New York Draft Exemptions, October 16, 1863; Doc (Box 5, Folder 6)
    Commutation Money Receipt indicating commutation money received from 18 men exempting them from the Federal Draft.
    Rudin # M-64
  - Drummer boy discharge, July 17, 1862; Doc S (Box 5, Folder 7)
    Certificate of Discharge for a 13 year old drummer boy by reason of a physical disability.
    Rudin # M-65
  - General Orders No. 3, February 6, 1865; Doc (Box 5, Folder 22)
    Act to provide for the appointment of a General in Chief of the Armies of the Confederate States.
    Rudin # A-139
  - General Orders No. 4, January 4, 1964; Doc (Box 5, Folder 8)
    Accused of desertion, Pvt. George Hoffer receives a sentence of 10 years at hard labor with a ball of 24 pounds attached to his leg by a chain four feet long.
    Rudin # M-73A
  - General Orders No. 24, February 21, 1865; Doc (Box 5, Folder 9)
    The restoration of the Union flag at Fort Sumter.
    Rudin # A-13B
  - General Orders No. 32, February 4, 1863; Doc (Box 5, Folder 10)
    Surgeon dismissed from the service for violation of 39th Article of War. (Fraudulent accounts)
    Rudin # M-73
  - General Orders No. 43, February 13, 1863; Doc (Box 5, Folder 11)
    Court martial of Major McKinstry, Quartermaster, charged with neglect of duty (buying in collusion with others) in 61 specifications. Lincoln approved sentence of dismissal from the service. Inked signature of General Hiram Scofield.
    Rudin # M-72
  - General Orders No. 53, December 2, 1863; Doc (Box 5, Folder 12)
    Court martials of deserters - men ordered to have their heads shaved and branded with the letter "D" and one man to be shot to death.
    Rudin # M-76
  - General Orders No. 147, May 26, 1863; Doc (Box 5, Folder 13)
    President Lincoln changes sentences of three soldiers.
    Rudin # M-67
  - General Orders No. 148, May 26, 1863; Doc (Box 5, Folder 14)
    Lincoln approves sentence of dishonorable discharge for a soldier who pleaded guilty to stealing from another private.
    Rudin # M-71A
  - General Orders No. 149, May 26, 1863; Doc (Box 5, Folder 15)
    Court martial of soldier for desertion and assault with intent to commit robbery and murder. Lincoln approves sentence to be shot.
    Rudin # M-76A
  - General Orders No. 190, June 25, 1863; Doc (Box 5, Folder 16)
    Pay schedule for men enlisting in the Regular Army offering premium, advanced pay, and bounty.
    Rudin # M-66
  - General Orders No. 209, July 7, 1863; Doc (Box 5, Folder 17)
    Court martial of a soldier found guilty of drunkenness on duty and conduct unbecoming an officer.
    Rudin # M-68
  - General Orders No. 230, July 23, 1863; Doc (Box 5, Folder 18)
    Court Martial found four men guilty of desertion, violation of oath of allegiance, and murder. Lincoln showed compassion and remitted all sentences. Two copies.
    Rudin # M-70, 75
  - General Orders No. 240, July 28, 1863; Doc (Box 5, Folder 19)
    Court Martial of two soldiers found guilty of desertion.
    Rudin # M-69
  - General Orders No. 267, August 3, 1863; Doc (Box 5, Folder 20)
    General Orders accusing eight different men of various charges punishable by a sentence of "To be shot to death".
    Rudin # M-74
  - General Orders No. 306, September 13, 1863; Doc (Box 5, Folder 21)
    Lincoln approves sentence of hanging for a soldier accused of being a guerilla.
    Rudin # M-71
  - Engraving of the naval engagement between the Merrimac and the Monitor. (Box 5, Folder 23)
    Rudin # M-77
  - Fort Sumter Note, April 15, 1861; Doc (Box 5, Folder 24)
    Twenty-five cent note - The Bank of the State of South Carolina - Fort Sumter on fire.
    Rudin # A-13A
  - Bounty: "Statement of Volunteer", March 14, 1864; Doc S (Box 5, Folder 25)
    Soldier receives a $300 bounty for enlisting.
    Rudin # M-41
  - Bounty Payment Bond, October 6, 1864; Doc S (Box 5, Folder 26)
    Payment Bond for $100 "on the call by the President for 500,000 men". To James Payne.
    Rudin # M-42
  - Bounty Receipt, October 8, 1864; Doc S (Box 5, Folder 27)
    County Bounty Receipt for $6000 for fifteen union soldiers who signed up for the Civil War for three years.
    Rudin # M-44
  - Bounty Receipt, August 20, 1864; Doc S (Box 5, Folder 28)
    Bounty receipt for $800 for two union soldiers who signed up for the Civil War for three years.
    Rudin # M-45
  - Bounty Fund Bond, February 15, 1865; Doc (Box 5, Folder 29)
    Bond used to raise funds to pay bounties to volunteers. ($300 bounty fund, interest 6%).
    Rudin # M-45AA
  - Civil War Recruiting Broadside, Doc (Box 5, Folder 30)
    Enlistment Recruiting Broadside for Mass. 2nd Regiment Heavy Artillery.
    Rudin # M-55
  - Confederate Circular, July 21, 1862; Doc (Box 5, Folder 31)
    Circular regarding officer's behavior in the field, by order of Brigadier General P.O. Hebert.
    Rudin # M-55A
  - Wallpaper Book, 1865; Booklet (Box 5, Folder 32)
    Confederate "Chaudron's Spelling Book" - Front and back covers printed on double-folded, ornate fancy wallpaper (see inside back cover and also "To the Public" preface referring to "scarcity of materials".) From the Henderschott Collection of Confederate Imprints.
    Rudin # M-97
  - Wallpaper envelope plus letter, January 11, 1863 (Box 5, Folder 33)
    Wallpaper envelope (no stamp) with letter from Sgt. Baker hand-carried to wife regarding clothing and naming of their baby.
    Rudin # M-98
  - Necessity Paper, ALS (Box 5, Folder 34)
    Being short of paper, soldier, Elisha O. Drake, writes on Soldier's Eagle Discharge Form. Discusses paying bills, re-enlisting, and photographs of Generals.
    Rudin # M-101
  - Necessity Paper, September 11, 1863; ALS (Box 5, Folder 35)
    Albert R. Whitney writes letter on Magnus hand colored patriotic song sheet discussing the campground, the lack of water, and the need for a box of clothing.
    Rudin # M-101A
  - Necessity Paper, January 1, 1863; Doc (Box 5, Folder 36)
    CSA North Carolina 25 Cent Note printed on back of 1863 North Carolina $20 Note.
    Rudin # M-101B
  - Necessity Paper, January 1, 1863; Doc (Box 5, Folder 37)
    Five Confederate Georgia Treasury Notes in denominations of 5 cents, 10 cents, 25 cents, 50 cents, and 75 cents, all printed on reverse of $4 note (not a popular denomination) because of the scarcity of paper.
    Rudin # M-101C
  - Necessity Stationary, ca. 1860 (Box 5, Folder 38)
    Confederate Patriotic Stationery with cannon, flag, and patriotic verse printed on brown Confederate necessity paper. Two different size letter sheets unused plus one envelope.
    Rudin # M-83
  - Necessity Paper, March 16, 1862; ALS (Box 5, Folder 39)
    Letter written by Union soldier to his sister on captured Confederate post office ledger.
    Rudin # M-83A
  - Necessity Paper, March 15, 1865; Doc (Box 5, Folder 40)
    Statement for a deceased Confederate soldier on necessity paper printed on official Republic of Mexico paper.
    Rudin # M-84
  - Necessity Paper, October 21, 1864 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    Hand made envelope from a printed sheet of a piano songbook. Postally used. Capt. HL Van Eaton.
    Rudin # M-85
  - Necessity Paper, Doc S (Box 6, Folder 2)
    Confederate Soldiers' Pass printed on verso of a Mississippi government form.
    Rudin # M-86A
  - Necessity Paper, February 2, 1863; ALS (Box 6, Folder 3)
    Soldier's letter (T.A. Taggart) on mocha colored necessity paper.
    Rudin # M-86B
  - Wallpaper newspaper, February 12, 1863 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    "The Junior Register" - Rare wallpaper edition printed on the back of wallpaper due to shortage of newsprint.
    Rudin # M-100
  - Necessity paper newspaper, April 14, 1864 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    Houston Daily Telegraph printed on tan corn husk paper.
    Rudin # M-100A
  - Wallpaper newspaper, October 2, 1863 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    The Tri-Weekly Telegraph printed on green corn husk paper.
    Rudin # M-100B
  - Civil War Pass, July 18, 1861; Doc S (Box 6, Folder 4)
    Civil War Pass allowing "F. Pool 3 days over the Bridges within the Original lines" signed by Captain Drake De Kay.
    Rudin # M-87
  - Password (confederate), May 16, 1861; Doc S (Box 6, Folder 5)
    An original password paper signed by Phinney Adjt.
    Rudin # M-88
  - Davis, Jefferson, 1867; Lithograph (Box 7, Folder 1)
    The Capture of Jeff Davis lithograph.
    Rudin # A-59
  - Davis, Jefferson, October 22, 1877; Pages: 1 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    Insightful letter into the thinking of Jefferson Davis.
    Rudin # A-60
  - Program for the second Inauguration of Jefferson Davis and Alexander Stephens, February 22, 1862; Pages: 4 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    Rudin # A-58
  - Davis, Jefferson, November 6, 1861; Election ballot (Box 6, Folder 8)
    Rudin # A-57
  - Miniature of Lee's General Orders No. 9 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    Lee's Farewell Address in a 1" square in the top left corner with hand-colored flags on a miniature cover. Written by Edward Pollard.
    Rudin # M-78
  - "Dix" Note (Box 6, Folder 10)
    Famous Dix Note that caused the South to be called "Dixie".
    Rudin # M-59